A Finding Aid to the Jean Cohen Papers, 1935-2012, in the Archives of American Art AAA.cohejean
Archives of American Art
Jean Cohen papers
1935-2012
AAA.cohejean
Archives of American Art
0.8 Linear feet
The papers of painter and educator Jean Cohen measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1935-2012. The collection consists of limited biographical material, a small amount of printed material, photographs of family and friends including Cohen's former husband, painter, Alex Katz, and a long correspondence with painter, Lois Dodd.
Cohen, Jean
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers were donated to the Archives of American Art in 2013 by Philip Douglas Heilman of Philip Douglas Fine Art, Cohen's dealer.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original materials requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Jean Cohen (1927-2013), an abstract painter, studied and worked in the New York area and was involved with the 1950s avant garde art scene.
Born in Brooklyn, New York, she was educated at Pratt Institute, Cooper Union, and the Skowhegan School of Painting in Maine. During the 1950s and 1960s she lived on Tenth Street in Manhattan and was a member of the Tenth Street Artists Galleries, also showing at the Tanger Gallery.
From 1950 to 1956 Cohen was married to painter, Alex Katz. She lived with painter, John Grillo, from 1957 to 1962. She later married photographer, Bill Miller in the 1970s. Cohen taught art at many institutions, including the Philadelphia College of Art, and had paintings in public collections such as the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Later in life, she moved to eastern Long Island, New York, where she continued to teach and work.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter and eduator Jean Cohen measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1935-2012. The collection consists of limited biographical material, a small amount of printed material, photographs of family and friends including Cohen's former husband, painter, Alex Katz, and a long correspondence with painter, Lois Dodd.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1961-2011 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1970-2011 (Box 1; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1960s-1970s (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 4: Subject Files, circa 1962-circa 1998 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Materials, circa 1962-2001 (Boxes 1-2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, 1935-2012 (Box 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Dodd, Lois, 1927-; Katz, Alex, 1927-; Art teachers--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Women artists--New York (State)--New York
- Biographical Material, circa 1961-2011; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes lists of Cohen's solo and group exhibitions, a detailed job application setting forth Cohen's education and teaching credits and a genealogy file concerning the O'Flaherty family, who were relatives of Cohen's significant other, Dan Burns.
  - Biographical Materials, 1961-2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Genealogy, 1961-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1970-2011; Series 2; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Letters are from friends and fellow painters. There also is a long correspondence with fellow painter, Lois Dodd.
  - Letters, 1974-2011; undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with Lois Dodd, 1970-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Writings, 1960s-1970s; Series 3; 1 Folders Box 1
  The writing "The Bar Haven is Northeast," by Dan Burns is a draft essay, which chronicles the activity of a fishing ship, the Bar Haven.
  - Writings by Don Burns, 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Subject Files, circa 1962- circa 1998; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  The Jack Micheline file contains a book of poems by Micheline entitled I Kiss Angels, letters from Micheline to Cohen and printed materials discussing Micheline's artwork in relation to "Beat Generation" artists. The other files contain printed material relating to Al Copley's art and poems and letters by Mary Fiori.
  - Jack Micheline, circa 1962-circa 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Al Copley, circa 1969-circa 1998 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mary Fiori, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Printed Material, circa 1962-2001; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Exhibition announcements are from solo and group shows of various abstract artists in downtown New York galleries. Catalogs are from exhibitions in New York and Texas.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1962-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Press Releases, 1984-2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs, 1935-2012; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  There are numerous black and white photographs of family and friends, many showing Jean Cohen alone or with friends, students, and colleagues. Also found are inventory record forms that identify some people, including Cohen's former husband, Alex Katz and other Skowhegan painters.
  - Jean Cohen, 1940s-2012 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Family and Friends, 1940s-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Family and Friends, 1935-circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Colleagues and Students, 1990-circa 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Accent Gallery, circa 1950s-2010 (Box 2, Folder 6)